<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd"
  xmlns:trackback="http://madskills.com/public/xml/rss/module/trackback/">
  <channel>
    <title>Tale of a Tiger</title>
    <link>http://sidhant.io/</link>
    <description>Developer Chronicles</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>'Gitting' started</title>
      <link>http://sidhant.io//gitting-started</link>
      <description>Recently, I got a chance to be a part of one of the most kick-ass communities, whose software basically rules
the tech world. Yeah, Git. The aim was to get my hands dirty with something new and amazing.
So though this post isn't as much about my experience there (so far, great), but rather a stash of useful commands that one may require when actually contributing to Git. I'll keep it updated as often as possible. Though the documentation for getting involved is very educative and covers everything you're required to do, I decided to write this post since I couldn't find a complete set of commands (and concepts) we need to actually get started. Man pages are nice, but nothing beats a well written tutorial, right?

</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <dc:date>2016-03-01T00:00:00+05:30</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The OpenCV Saga</title>
      <link>http://sidhant.io//the-opencv-saga</link>
      <description>### Ch. 1 : I See You

</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <dc:date>2015-10-20T00:00:00+05:30</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bling Bling Blink</title>
      <link>http://sidhant.io//bling-blink-blink</link>
      <description>Hey, do you use Google Chrome most of the time? All the time? Good for you. 'Cause I don't. I like Firefox better. I have my own reasons (not getting into that here). But you know what, I'm jealous of you. No seriously, I am jealous of Chrome users. I mean, you have an extension for everything. Literally. Need something to dim the webpages at night? Bang! There's an extension. Need a prettier new tab page? Boom! There you have it. And why do they have to be pretty? Why does every extension in Google Chrome have to be pretty and smooth and bursting with colors? What is it, Disneyland? If you've read my last blog post, you'd probably know what this is one is about. This post is about... (drum rolls) ... another Firefox add-on. This time, it's about [Blink](https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/blink/). A Firefox add-on I made to make the new tab page more interesting. Here's how it started:

</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <dc:date>2015-09-15T00:00:00+05:30</dc:date>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Into the darkness</title>
      <link>http://sidhant.io//into-the-darkness</link>
      <description>Being a software developer usually means long hours of working on computer, staring at the screen as if the meaning of life was hidden somewhere in those lines of code. But developer or not, looking at bright screens for longer durations is very straining to the eyes for everyone. So I prefer setting my IDE's theme to Darkula, or a similar dark theme, to save my eyes from being scorched. And have to admit, it's very cozy. The nice and dark background with dim-florescent text soothes the eye like the cool brook water to the lonely traveler.

</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <dc:date>2015-06-29T00:00:00+05:30</dc:date>
    </item>
    <dc:date>2016-03-01T00:00:00+05:30</dc:date>
  </channel>
</rss>